Okay בקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is כ"ב, chaf bet,
22. We pick up with the משנה mishna on כ"א עמוד ב',
chaf alef amud bet, and we are continuing to deal with the
materials with which a גט get can be written with, the ink,
the paper, and then we dealt with the idea of if it
was written on a horn of a cow or on the arm
of a slave, you have to give the slave, obviously you can't
cut off the arm, but you have to give off the whole
cow and it seems like if you cut the horn of the
cow off that would invalidate the גט get because that would be
considered lacking cutting, מחוסר קציצה, mechusar k'tzitza, even though it didn't need
to be cut, somehow the act of cutting is considered to be
a problem when it comes in between, and we discussed תוספות Tosafot
who said, who raised the question, what if you were just talking
about cutting a גט get from a larger piece of paper? If
you just trim off some like, you know, some margins, that was
assumed to be trivial. But if it's somewhat transformative, that the גט
get is on a small, is on a piece of a very
large piece and you cut it away from a bigger piece of
paper,
תוספות Tosafot had actually a debate whether or not that would be
good, a real case, whether that was debated whether or not that
invalidates the גט. get. But תוספות Tosafot is more inclined to say
that the only act of cutting that invalidates is when you're cutting
it off from something that is either growing like picking off a
leaf of a tree,
or it was written on the leaf and then you picked off
the leaf, or from an animal that was, so it was the
horn of a cow, and then the cutting off is seen as
more transformative. But that raises the important question of what's considered this
act of cutting or lacking a cutting that actually is a problem
between the writing and the giving of the גט. get. So with
that in mind actually we look at the next משנה mishna which
in some ways continues the conversation. So let's look at the משנה,
mishna, let's just read the משנה mishna just to get started and
take the question on כ"ב עמוד ב'. chaf bet amud bet. אין
כותבין במחובר לקרקע, ein kotvin bimchubar l'karka,
you do not write on something that's attached to the ground. כתבו
במחובר, ktavo bimchubar,
if you wrote it on something attached, תלשו וחתמו ונתנו לה, tlasho
vechatmo venasno lah,
and then you uprooted it, you picked the leaf off the tree,
you cut the tree down, and then you signed it and gave
it to her, כשר, kasher, it's כשר. kasher. Because that seems to
be emphasizing the position of, well, the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask, make up your mind, do you or don't you? But a
good way to read this is that this is רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, that ultimately focuses on the signing of the גט, get, so
you don't write לכתחילה l'chatchila on מחובר, mchubar, this came up in
the very beginning of the מסכת, masechet, because you might come to
sign it, but בדיעבד b'diavad if you did write, as long as
you signed it once the thing was cut down, you're okay. So
that's one way of reading it, especially because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
now is the next line. רבי יהודה פוסל עד שיהא כתיבתו וחתימתו
בתלוש, Rabbi Yehuda posel ad sheyhei ktivato vechatimato b'talush, but רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda requires both the signing, the writing and the signing to
be when it's cut down, because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the
one that says, you know, that against רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would be saying that it goes by the writing,
it's not עדי חתימה כרתי, eidei chatima karti, it's not the signing
turns it into a גט, get, it's the witnesses that are external
when it's handed over, and therefore the writing of the גט get
focuses on the actual writing, not on the signing. Right, if you
remember from the very beginning of the מסכת, masechet, the גמרא Gemara
connected those opinions. If you say עדי חתימה כרתי, eidei chatima karti,
the signing is what makes it into a גט get and those
are the signatures, and those are the witnesses that count, then the
פסוק pasuk that says וכתב v'katav emphasizes really it becoming a גט
get through the signing. So all the requirements focus on the signing.
So that would be the first opinion that says as long as
it's signed once it's not מחובר, mchubar, you're okay. Whereas רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda would be saying that maybe both the writing and the
signing, or at least, or certainly the writing though, maybe so עדי
מסירה כרתי eidei mesira karti is one way of understanding that and
therefore it's not the signatures that are so important, and therefore the
emphasis of the תורה Torah on the writing, so the writing it
has to be תלוש, talush, it is not enough that it be
signed בתלוש. b'talush. Okay, that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה בן
בתירה אומר אין כותבין לא על נייר מחוק ולא על דפתרא, Rabbi
Yehuda ben Beteira omer ein kotvin lo al niyar machuk v'lo al
diftra,
you do not write on erased paper or on דפתרא, diftra, which
is a certain type of a קלף, klaf, where were you to
erase afterwards it would not be obvious that you had erased, מפני
שיכול להזדייף, mipnei sheyakhol l'hizdayef, because it can be forged, because basically
a person can write a גט, get, sign it, and then you
can go ahead and maybe there was a תנאי tnai in the
גט get and then the woman could erase the תנאי tnai and
put some other line in it. So it's not, you could even
sort of say that you could, a person could have written an
IOU for a hundred dollars on such a thing and then the
woman could scrape off everything from the top, leave the signatures on
the bottom and replace the top with a גט. get. So therefore
you cannot do it on that because who knows what was actually,
whether there were any changes that took place in the document. וחכמים
מכשירין v'chachamim machshirin and the חכמים chachamim allow it. That's pretty, you
know, it's crazy. How could they allow it? It's a very reasonable
question. How do you know what was there originally? Maybe something was
erased and changed. So the גמרא Gemara again will say that this
חכמים chachamim is עדי מסירה כרתי eidei mesira karti and therefore if
you need there to be witnesses when it's handed over, then the
גט get does not have to, then even if in theory you
know, you in the end are trusting. the witnesses who were physically
present and they saw the גט Get at the and they read
it, presumably they read it, and they saw it at the time,
and so that would be suffice and maybe it got changed later
but in the end you'll always have those witnesses. So we'll talk,
we'll unpack that in the גמרא Gemara as well. So there are
these these questions about what type of document and whether it has
to be מחובר Mechubar but to some degree ties back into very
central questions about עדי מסירה Edei Mesirah and עדי חתימה. Edei Chasima.
Yeah, you're
good. There's a question. You're good. Okay. So, now,
what was I going to say here? Ah. Now an interesting thing
just to raise parenthetically is: Why can't you write it במחובר? b'Mechubar?
Well, you would think because there's no way to give it במחובר,
b'Mechubar, but I want to remind you that yesterday we talked about
writing, having a גט Get in the hand of an עבד Eved
and then gifting over the slave and that was considered as a
giving of the גט Get because it was the slave holding the
גט Get at the same time and then by the taking possession
of the slave, the woman also took possession of the גט Get
that was in his hand. So one could raise a question about
why can't you do the same even if something is מחובר לקרקע?
Mechubar l'Karka? You have it written on a bark of a tree,
instead of one of those hearts with the 'Sally loves John' with
the
arrow through it, you write הרי את מגורשת ממני Harei At Megoreshet
Mimeni on a tree, okay? And then you actually give your wife
the deed of the property and she takes possession of that and
that would be a נתינת הגט. Netinas HaGet. Okay? So the גמרא
Gemara never exactly spells out why מחובר Mechubar is no good, but
it seems like even if in theory you could give it, there's
some intrinsic פסול Psul with it being מחובר. Mechubar. Okay. רמב"ם Rambam
understands that as this problem of מחוסר קציצה Mechusar Ketzitzah because it
requires being cutting down but one it so little begs the question,
why does it require being cut, why can't you just gift the
whole property? But somehow we're assuming that no, for it to be
a גט Get it has to be somehow chattel and movable and
it can't be just connected to the ground. Okay, and therefore the
line winds up being in the משנה, Mishnah, which is: At what
stage does it become the גט? Get? At the
writing or only at the signing? So if you wrote it and
then cut it down and then signed it, would that be good
or not? Yes.
And I would have said, you take a tree on a property,
so you could give it, it wouldn't work on a tree, you
know what I mean? Forget about whether it's מחובר. Mechubar. Why? Because
it says like a ספר. Sefer. Is a tree a ספר? Sefer?
So yeah, so you could say that's a requirement of ספר, Sefer,
which is similar to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGlili who said
that something can't be a ספר Sefer if it's on בעל חי
Ba'al Chai or food. But the Rabbis disagreed and they said there
is no limit about the object, just the דברים. Devarim. So all
I'm saying is, yes, we could say that there we could speculate
that it doesn't count as a ספר, Sefer, but the גמרא Gemara
never spells out what the מחובר Mechubar problem is. It takes it
for granted that it can't be מחובר. Mechubar. Okay. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. כתבה על
המחובר Katavah al haMechubar and אמרת רישא אין כותבין. Amarta Reisha ein
kotvin. It says you don't write it on מחובר Mechubar and then
it says but if you wrote it on מחובר Mechubar and you
signed it once it was cut down, you're
okay. So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel,
והוא ששייר מקום התורף. v'hu sheshiyar makom haToref. So the first thing
is, wow, what we mean is: Don't write even the boilerplate there's
two phrases, טופס Tofes and תורף. Toref. טופס Tofes I don't know
exactly how they mean what they mean, but I mean תורף, Toref,
but טופס Tofes means the boilerplate and the תורף Toref means the
essence of it, like the fill-in-the-blanks parts, the names, the places, and
so on. Okay, so even if you say that the כתיבה Ketivah
has these requirements, not the signing, that it becomes a גט Get
through the writing and it they require לשמה, Lishmah, they require all
those things it's not the boilerplate part of it. It's only the
fill-in-the-blanks part, only the תורף, Toref, the essential part of it, that
has those requirements. So he's saying that this could all follow רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of עדי מסירה כרתי, Edei Mesirah Karthi, and nevertheless,
when it says that if you signed it afterwards you're okay, it
doesn't really mean signed it afterwards you're okay. It means that if
you cut it down and filled in the blanks afterwards. Of course,
that's a creative reread. The משנה Mishnah says you signed it afterwards.
But anyway, והוא ששייר מקום התורף. v'hu sheshiyar makom haToref. You left
over the essential part of the part of it. And that, now,
by the way, the הרי את מותרת לכל אדם, Harei At Muteres
l'chol adam, even though that is boilerplate because every גט Get says
הרי את מותרת לכל אדם, Harei At Muteres l'chol adam, that still
is the תורף. Toref. That's like the punchline of the גט. Get.
Okay, so you left off all of the essential parts and then
that you filled in after you cut it down. That's when the
משנה Mishnah says it's okay.
Wait, so what did you put in before? What was the names?
Yeah.
Well no, but the date would be... well I don't know if
the date would be a תורף Toref because it's... I'm not sure.
I think it's the names and הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. Harei
At Muteres l'chol adam. What does רש"י Rashi say here?
Yeah, well תורף Toref includes the date, the names of the men...
of the names... the date... the גט Get was drawn... right, those
are the תורף. Toref. Everything everything that's not boilerplate, right, the names
and the date and the time... the names and the date and
the place.
But I'm pretty... but הרי את מותרת לכל אדם... Harei At Muteres
l'chol adam... he doesn't say... they don't mention הרי את מותרת לכל
אדם... Harei At Muteres l'chol adam... I mean רש"י Rashi says גילויו
של שטר מקום האיש והאשה והזמן. gilluyav shel shetar makom ha'ish v'ha'ishah
v'hazman. I'm pretty sure... there you go, I'm getting it from רש"י.
Rashi. But I'm pretty sure that הרי את מותרת לכל אדם Harei
At Muteres l'chol adam is also included because that's like the essence
of the גט. Get. Anyway,
so but then there's all these lines that connect those facts, you
know, think about a כתובה, Ketubah, right. All right, well, we should
read it. I think that's actually the רי״ף *Rif*. I mean, I
don't want to digress too much, but I think if you want
to take a look, we should actually have, I think, the רי״ף
*Rif* has the basic declaration
of והרי את מותרת לכל
אדם *veharei at muteret lechol
adam* and all these points are very good. Yeah, take a look
at the רי״ף *Rif* on page, well, I guess we'll digress for
a minute, page מ״ה עמוד ב׳ *mem hey amud bais* in the
דפי הרי״ף *dapei harif*. Okay,
he has it, he says: בכך וכך בשבת בכך וכך לירח פלוני
בשנת כך וכך לבריאת עולם במניינא דרגילנא למימני ביה בדוכתא פלונית *bechach
vechach beshabos bechach vechach liyereach ploni bishnas kach vechach livrias olam beminyana
deregila leminyana be beduchta plonis* the counting that we do in this
place, היך אנא פלוני בר פלוני וכל שום דאית לי *heich ana
ploni bar ploni vechol shum deis li* how I so-and-so and any
other name I have, ממתא פלונית *mimasa plonis* from so-and-such a city,
צביתי ברעות נפשי *tsevis birus nafshi* I desired with my own free
will, דלא אניסא *delo anisa* without being forced, ופטרית ושבקית ותריכית *ufataris
veshavakis vesarichis* and I released and the whatever divorced and divorced, יתיכי
ליכי את פלונית בת פלוני *yasichi lichi ant plonis bas ploni* you
yourself, you so-and-so, וכל שום דאית ליכי ממתא פלונית *vechol shum deis
lichi mimasa plonis* and any other name you have from so-and-such a
city, דהוית אינתתי מן קדמת דנא *dehavis intasi min kadmas dena* that
you were my wife prior to this, וכדו *vechado* and with this,
פטרית ושבקית ותריכית יתיכי ליכי את פלונית בת פלוני וכל שום דאית
ליכי ממתא פלונית *ufataris veshavakis vesarichis yasichi lichi ant plonis bas ploni
vechol shum deis lichi mimasa plonis* ודי תהויין רשאה ושלטאה בנפשיכי *vedi
sehavin rasha veshalta benafshichi* you should be permitted
control over your yourself,
meaning you're in your own control, למהך להתנסבא לכל גבר די תצביין
*lemehach lehinsava lechol gevar di sisevin* to go and marry any man
that you desire, ואינש לא lo ימחה בידייכי מן יומא דנן ולעלם
*venish lo yimcha biyadaichi min yoma dena uleolam* nobody should prevent you
from doing so and from this day forward, והרי את מותרת לכל
אדם *veharei at muteret lechol adam* and you're permitted to every man,
ודן די יהוי ליכי מינאי *vaden di lehevei lichi minai* this should
be for you from me, ספר תירוכין וגט פיטורין ואיגרת שבוקין *sefer
teiruchin veget piturin veigeres shevukin* a bill of divorce and a bill
of divorce and a bill of divorce, כדת משה וישראל *kedas Moshe
veYisrael*. Okay, so there you go.
I mean, do you have
to say all that now? What? Yeah, yeah. So half of it
is basically the Torah. Anyway, fine. Okay, so back to the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, אמר amar רב יהודה
אמר שמואל והוא ששייר מקום התורף *amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel vehu
sheshiyer mekom hatoref*. So you left over when it says that you
filled in the blanks, when it says you did it after you
cut it down, it doesn't mean you just signed it after you
cut it down that it's okay, but you filled in the blanks
and you did the הרי את מותרת לכל אדם *harei at muteret
lechol adam*. You did the essence of it after you cut it
down. וכן אמר רב אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא והוא ששייר מקום התורף
*vechen amar Rav Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya vehu sheshiyer mekom hatoref*. And
then it could be going even if you say that the עדי
מסירה כרתי *eidi mesirah karshei* that the עיקר *ikkar* is the writing.
וכן אמר רבה בר בר חנה Chana אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
והוא ששייר מקום התורף *vechen amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan vehu sheshiyer mekom hatoref*. רבי אלעזר היא Rabbi Elazar hi, דאמר
עדי מסירה כרתי De-amar edei mesira karsi, *Rabbi Elazar hi d'amar eidi
mesirah karshei* that the physical witnesses who are present make it a
גט get *get* and the writing makes it a גט get. *get*
and not the signing. And therefore if you're going to do the,
if it's going to be כשר Kasher, *kasher*, you have to do
the, then you have to actually write it after it's cut down.
So when it says you signed it after it's cut down, it
meant you wrote the essential parts after it was cut down. Okay,
והכי קאמר *vehachi ka'amar* and here's how you have to read it.
אין כותבין תורף שמא יכתוב תורף *ein kotvin toref shema yichtov toref*.
Don't write the boilerplate when it's attached lest you come to write
the essential parts. כתבו לטופס ותלשו וכתבו לתורף ונתנו לה כשר kasher?
*kasavo l'tofes vesalsho vechasavo l'toref venasno la kasher*. But if you did
write the boilerplate and you cut it down and then you wrote
the essential parts, you filled in the blanks and you wrote הרי
את מותרת *harei at muteret* and you gave it to her, כשר
kasher, *kasher* it is kosher. Okay, so it re-reads the line that
says חתמו *chasamo* you signed it and says חתמו *chasamo* doesn't mean
you signed it, it means you filled in the essential parts after
it was cut down. ריש לקיש אמר חתמו שנינו *Resh Lakish amar
chatamo shaninu*. Now, ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* says you can't say that.
The משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* says what you did after it was cut
down was you signed it. So you can't re-read the word signed
it to mean you filled in the essential parts. רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir היא דאמר עדי חתימה כרתי edei chasima karsi, *Rabbi Meir hi
d'amar eidi chasimah karshei*. It's רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* that
says it becomes a גט get. *get* through the signing. That's clearly
the פשט pshat *pshat* of the משנה *Mishnah*. והכי קאמר *vehachi ka'amar*
and here's how you have to read it. אין כותבין תורף *ein
kotvin toref* you don't even write the essential parts while it's מחובר
m'chubar *mechubar* attached, גזירה שמא יחתום *gezeirah shema yichtom* lest you come
to actually finish it and sign it while it's attached. כתבו לתורף
ותלשו וחתמו ונתנו לה כשר kasher, *kasavo l'toref vesalsho vechasamo venasno la
kasher*. But if you wrote the essential parts while it was attached
and then you cut it down and then you signed it, as
long as you signed it after it was cut down, then בדיעבד
*bediavad* it's okay because it's the signing that makes it into a
גט get, *get* and only as long as the signing has to
occur when it is no longer attached to the ground. Okay, כתבו
על החרס *kasavo al hacheres*. Now, so that's two readings of the
משנה *Mishnah*. Again, not explaining why it's invalid when it's attached, that's
taken for granted. But the question about when it, what part has
to be detached, when is the משנה *Mishnah* saying it's okay, is
that we're going רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar. *Rabbi Elazar* and it has
to be that the תורף *toref*, the actual writing of it, the
essential parts have to be when it's already cut down, or only
as the פשט pshat. *pshat* of the משנה *Mishnah*, only the signing
because we're going like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*.
Okay, now. Can we get like some sense behind this מחלוקת *machlokes*
of the relationship as stable as this is, is more like מטלטלין
metaltelin, *metaltelin* than it is like קרקע karka, *karka*. In other words,
it has to be, it has to be movable.
That's very nicely symbolic. Okay, I don't know, maybe, I don't think
that's why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes, but it's a nice, symbolically
nice. Okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. Okay, now, כתבו על חרס של עציץ נקוב Ketavo al cheresh
shel atzitz nakuv, *kasavo al cheres shel atzitz nakuv*. Let's say you
wrote it on the, on the pottery part of a, of a
planter, of a flower pot that has a hole in it. Now
we have to notice that if you've got a flower pot that's
got a hole in it, that's considered מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka okay?
Because here's, I know, you're right, the גמרא Gemara is obsessed with
it. Here's your קרקע, karka, okay, and here's your, here's your flower
pot,
and here's your, right, here's your nice little flower pot, and here's
your flower that's growing out of your flower pot, okay? And your
flower pot is filled with dirt.
So, soil, thank you. Technically speaking, soil. Now if it's got a
hole in it, then we basically look at this as sort of
like a just a continuation of like a big like a little
lump of soil, right? We see the hole sort of connecting to
the ground underneath. The funny thing is even if it's a little
off the ground and there's air space between it, and we just
sort of see this as all part of the soil and it's
growing and it's all connected to the ground if it's got a
hole in the bottom of the עציץ, atzitz, okay? So you have
this flower pot with a hole in it, and you wrote the
גט get on the actual pottery of the pot. You actually wrote
it on the pot itself, not on the plant, okay? So, כתבו
על חרס של עציץ נקוב, atzitz nakuv. you wrote it on the
pot itself. כשר, it's kosher. דשקיל ליה ויהיב ליה ניהלה, D'shakil lei
v'yahiv lei nihala, because he can just give the woman the pot.
Now,
על עלה של עציץ נקוב, Al ala shel atzitz nakuv, if you
wrote it on the leaf of the plant growing in this flower
pot. אביי אמר כשר, Abaye amar kasher, it's kosher. רבא אמר פסול,
Rava amar pasul, Rava said it's not kosher. אביי אמר כשר, Abaye
amar kasher, Abaye says it's kosher. Why? דשקיל ליה ויהיב ליה ניהלה,
D'shakil lei v'yahiv lei nihala, because you just go go give her
the pot, same thing with the leaf on it. רבא אמר פסול,
Rava amar pasul, Rava said it's pasul, גזירה שמא יקטום, gezeira shema
yiktom, it's pasul because we're afraid you'll pluck off the leaf. But
we're not afraid you're going to like, I don't know, break the
flower pot. Now, תוספות Tosafot has a whole question about wait a
minute,
like why would it be, first of all the פשט of this
גמרא, Gemara. why aren't we afraid you'll break the flower pot or
similar that you'll pluck off the leaf? It could just be it's
easier to pluck off a leaf than it is to break a
flower pot. But תוספות Tosafot uses this its case to discuss his
question about what type of a cutting afterwards invalidates the גט. get
One way of reading this is only when you cut something from
being מחובר m'chubar does it invalidate the גט. get So if you
pluck off a leaf, that invalidates it, right? Because it was מחובר
m'chubar, and now you made it non-מחובר, m'chubar, that's why it was
an עציץ נקוב. atzitz nakuv, If you broke a piece of pottery,
that's like cutting off the small piece of the paper from the
large piece of paper, that would not invalidate. So that's one way
of understanding that. The, okay, and that's probably more closer to פשט.
But תוספות Tosafot has another problem or he makes a point. Let's
say it does become invalid when you pluck cut something off that's
growing. When I give the woman this flower pot, right, is it
still attached, is is the hole still, is it on the, is
it on the dirt, okay, is it still considered מחובר, m'chubar okay?
So would that be כשר? Let's say you have something that is
movable but still considered קרקע, karka. right? Can I give that as
a גט, get okay? So that תוספות Tosafot raises that question. תוספות
Tosafot assumes, it's not clear what the answer is, the גמרא's Gemara,
not clear about that. תוספות Tosafot assumes that if I give this
to a woman to divorce her, I have to actually put it
like on top of a table where it's no longer open air
space between the bottom of the pot and the dirt. That makes
it no longer מחובר m'chubar. if I actually have something between it
and the dirt, okay, as opposed to air. Air would still be
considered מחובר. m'chubar. So that's a חידוש. chiddush. Number one is, as
this, it's not a גט get because it's considered מחובר. m'chubar, I
can give it to the woman without plucking the leaf off and
make it non-מחובר, m'chubar, but that's not considered cutting it, right? It
becomes very funny. I can't pluck the leaf off. By making it
physically non-מחובר, m'chubar I've considered to transform it, to cut it, to
change it, and I've invalidated. But to give the flower pot in
a way that makes it non-מחובר m'chubar without physically changing it, by
putting it on top of a table, that actually is כשר, right?
So it's a very funny middle ground. The גמרא's Gemara not clear
about any of this, right? You could have said in the גמרא
Gemara that that any cutting invalidates, and if I did break the
pot, if it was written on the pot and I broke the
pot it would be פסול. pasul. That's one opinion in תוספות. Tosafot.
You could say only changing something from מחובר m'chubar. invalidates. But then
you have to ask if I give her the flower pot when
it's כשר, does it have to still be attached to the ground
or is it invalid if it's attached to the ground, right, if
it's, I mean, if the hole is sort of connected to the
ground. And here תוספות's Tosafot assumption is that you actually have to
separate the hole from the ground because you have to make the
גט get. non-מחובר. m'chubar But if you make the גט get, non-מחובר
m'chubar without physically changing it, that's okay. To pluck the leaf is
not okay. To make it non-מחובר m'chubar? without physically changing it, according
to the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, is necessary and okay. Alright,
so anyway, very interesting about how this fits into this whole idea
of קציצה. ketzitzah.
Why written on the pot and you break the pot, that's like
treating the pot as if it were מחובר? mechubar.
No, תוספות Tosafot says if it's written on the pot and you
break
the
pot actually. Right. If you wrote it on the pot and left
the pot sitting on the dirt, then it would be invalid because
it would be מחובר. mechubar. And a גט get, can't be מחובר.
mechubar, If you wrote it on the leaf and then put the
flower pot on the table, you've made it לא מחובר, lo mechubar,
so it's a כשר גט, kosher get, but you haven't physically changed
it, so it's not considered that you did an act of קציצה,
ketzitzah, and that's okay. So very walking a tightrope there. Anyway, none
of that is clear in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, now the גמרא,
Gemara the one on the previous דף, daf, יצא זה שמחוסר קציצה.
yatza ze shemechusar ketzitzah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. continues to
discuss this case of not really, we're going to leave גיטין Gittin
for a minute and discuss הלכות של קניינים hilchot shel kinyanim about
this flower pot. עציץ של אחד וזרעים של אחר. atzitz shel echad
vezeraim shel acher. Okay, it's my flower pot and it's Michael's seeds,
presumably it's also Michael's dirt, I'm assuming, though that's not spelled out.
But we're going to assume that it's Michael's dirt and his seeds.
Okay, now, מכר בעל עציץ לבעל זרעים. machar baal atzitz lebaal zeraim.
Michael wants to buy my pot. Fine, I'll sell it to you.
So he just needs to take possession of the actual pot itself.
The dirt and the seeds are his. Well, the pot is considered
מטלטלין, metaltelin. chattel. How do you take possession of chattel? By משיכה.
meshichah.
So, כיון שמשך קנה. keivan shemashach kanah. He does a משיכה meshichah
on the pot, he owns the pot. Now, מכר בעל זרעים לבעל
עציץ. machar baal zeraim lebaal atzitz. Let's say I want to take
possession of the dirt and the seeds. Okay, what do I have
to do? So, לא קנה עד שיחזיק בזרעים. lo kanah ad sheyachzik
bazeiraim. So the dirt and the seeds because the flower pot has
a hole in it is considered קרקע. karka. It's very interesting, it's
movable קרקע. karka, It's sort of like עציץ נקוב, atzitz nakuv,
yeah, we clearly we're talking about that. It's sort of like the
case about an עבד. eved. An עבד eved has a status like
קרקע, karka, but he's not מחובר, if you think about it, right?
He's not physically attached and anchored in a place. So this too
is קרקע, karka? but it is movable. So you could have asked
how are you קונה koneh movable קרקע? karka. Maybe it's enough to
do a משיכה, meshichah, like I can actually move this קרקע. karka,
But no, it says since it's considered קרקע, karka, I actually have
to do a קנין kinyan that I do on קרקע, karka which
is חזקה. chazakah. I could also do כסף. kesef. רש"י Rashi said
if I paid for it, then that also works by real estate,
it doesn't work by chattel. But I haven't yet paid for it,
okay, I'm going to owe him the money. Welcome, welcome. So, but
what I'm going to do is I'm going to do a חזקה.
chazakah. The way you do a חזקה chazakah on קרקע karka, is
that you actually go ahead and you do something to improve the
land. If I'm taking possession of your house, so or your field,
I go ahead and I like dig a furrow in it, you
know, I knock a stake into the ground. So I, yeah, maybe
I don't know, maybe I water the stuff or something. I think
that that would work. Yeah, you know, whatever I do, I do
some type of a thing to improve the soil in that pot.
I do a חזקה chazakah on the soil. Okay, now, עד שיחזיק
בזרעים. ad sheyachzik bazeiraim. So I have to actually do a
חזקה. chazakah. עציץ וזרעים של אחד ומכרן לאחר. atzitz vezeraim shel echad
umacharan leachar. Now I own the whole pot with the flower, the
pot and the dirt and the soil and the seeds, and I'm
going to sell them to my friend חנה here who just came
in and I want to give it to her as a welcome
gift. Okay, a nice plant. Okay, so what does she have to
do to take possession of it? Okay, so, החזיק בזרעים
קנה עציץ. hechzik bazeiraim kanah atzitz. As long as, once she does
the חזקה chazakah on the actual seeds, she's going to go ahead
and water the seeds let's say, and she'll do a חזקה chazakah
on the seeds, which is a חזקה chazakah on קרקע, karka. she
automatically owns the flower pot which is מטלטלין. metaltelin, Now why is
that? A חזקה chazakah doesn't work on מטלטלין, metaltelin a חזקה chazakah
only works on the קרקע. karka, How does that give her possession
of the flower pot?
So, קנה עציץ, kanah atzitz, וזו ששנינו, vezu sheshaninu, this is what
we teach, נכסים שאין להם אחריות, nechasim she'ein lahem achrayut, land that
does not have sort of liens on it, meaning chattel, נקנים עם
נכסים שיש להם אחריות, niknim im nechasim sheyesh lahem achrayut, can be
possessed together with land that does have liens on it, meaning with
real estate, בכסף ובשטר ובחזקה, bechesef uvishtar uvachazakah, with the way you
possess real estate, with paying the money, with doing a חזקה, chazakah,
or with giving the document, which means when I buy קרקע, karka.
I can buy מטלטלין metaltelin to piggyback a קנין kinyan of מטלטלין
metaltelin, that I do through that קנין kinyan of קרקע. karka Now,
that's called a קנין אגב. kinyan agav. Now normally the way it
gets talked about in the גמרא Gemara is it could be completely
like unrelated מטלטלין, metaltelin. like basically I'm trying to
sell Michael, I don't know, ten thousand boxes of widgets that I
have in my warehouse. Now what's he going to do? He's going
to do משיכה meshichah and that's going to be a pain in
the neck, right? So what I'm going to do, and anyway they're
in another state and he needs to take possession of them right
then and now, so what I'm going to do is I'm actually
going to sell him a square inch of real estate, okay, maybe
he'll sell it back to me afterwards, but this will get the
job done,
and by him giving me a dollar for that square inch of
real estate, by taking possession because קרקע karka is נקנה בכסף, niknah
bechesef, then I'll say אגב, agav, in together with that קרקע karka,
you should go ahead and take possession of all those ten thousand
boxes of widgets. Okay, and that works. By taking possession of קרקע,
karka? you can piggyback on it, link to it מטלטלין. metaltelin, Now,
do they have to be on the קרקע? karka No, they don't.
Now there is discussions in the גמרא Gemara about צבורים ומונחים בתוכו
tziburim u'munachim betocho etc., but in the end we don't פוסקין pasken
that that's necessary. It might also be because all קרקע karka. is
considered to be connected, so to some degree, right, it's all part
of the earth. So somehow if a piece of something that's connected
to where those things, I don't know, but what if they're, what
if I had them hovering with a magnet above the earth? I
don't know.
Anyway, who says the same way that the עציץ atzitz if there's
air between the ground...
Yeah, but anyway, but you don't need, normally by אגב agav you
don't need it to be physically present, although there's a discussion in
the גמרא Gemara about צבורים ומונחים בתוכו. tziburim u'munachim betocho. This case
is, of course, much better than that. This case might be the
actual paradigm on which the other stuff is based because, as was,
you know, Sam correctly pointed out, this makes intuitive sense. I'm basically
selling you, let's imagine I'm selling you a furnished house. Right? I'm
selling you my field and when you're going to buy my field,
you will buy all of the wheat and the cows and the
tractors and everything on the field. Okay, so that might be the
paradigm on which the קנין אגב kinyan agav is based, even if
להלכה l'halacha you don't actually need the other stuff to be physically
on the land. So this case is obviously much better because it's
actually literally like an extension of it and attached to it, which
תוספות Tosafos says might lead to a נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Because
when I say you're going to get the 10,000 widgets by buying
this square inch of land, I have to say, 'Be קונה koneh
those widgets אגב agav this land.' I have to explicitly link them.
Okay, whereas here, it could be that I don't even have to
say that. If you look at תוספות Tosafos because it's like just
intrinsically seen as one. Look at תוספות, Tosafos, he says, החזיק
בזרעים קנה עציץ צריך עיון אם צריך לומר אגב וקני. hechzik b'izroyim
kanah atzitz tzarich iyun im tzarich lomar agav u'kni. Go possess it
through, you know, on top of the other thing. כמו בעלמא, k'mo
b'alma, כי דאמרינן בפרק קמא דקידושין, ki d'amrinan b'perek kama d'Kiddushin, או
שמא הכא לא צריך, o shema hacha lo tzarich, דכיון דצריך עציץ
לזרעים, d'keivan d'tzarich atzitz l'zra'im, since the... I don't know if the
עציץ atzitz seems to זרעים zra'im or the זרעים zra'im needs the
עציץ, atzitz, but whatever, בטל אגב זרעים. batel agav zra'im. So since
the... so since you know, the flowerpot is considered sort of an
extension of and secondary to the זרעים. zra'im. And if I'm taking
possession of the זרעים, zra'im, the flowerpot naturally comes with. I don't
have to explicitly say, 'Go אגב וקני,' agav u'kni, connected,
possess it, I'm selling it to you. But even when I'm clearly
selling you, when if it's a normal קנין אגב kinyan agav I
have to use the word, 'Possess it אגב agav the קרקע.' karka.
And here תוספות Tosafos says maybe not because maybe here it's considered
essentially one unit.
Yes. And the second thing is when is an un-נקוב? un-nikuv? He's
mainly talking about if it's upon a wheel, it's non-underground. Yeah, so
it counts as מטלטלין, metaltelin. right? Right. And then the third thing
is, you know, just out of curiosity, like let's say it makes
a difference to condo or co-op? Co-op they don't technically own the
real estate, they own shares in a...
All right, I'm not going to discuss that now. All right, let's
take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this. Exactly. Okay, so it says...
okay, here's. Now, החזיק
בעציץ אף עציץ לא קנה, hechzik b'atzitz af atzitz lo kanah, but
if I was trying to sell you both, I was trying to
give Chava this welcome plant here, and instead of watering the seeds,
she just drew the flowerpot to her. Okay, actually she didn't draw
it, she didn't do a משיכה. meshicha. If she did a משיכה
meshicha at least she'd own the flowerpot. She actually did a חזקה
chazaka on the flowerpot. How did she do a חזקה chazaka on
the flowerpot? She tried to improve it. I don't know, she painted
it or something. Okay?
So אף עציץ לא קנה. af atzitz lo kanah. She doesn't even
own the flowerpot, let alone not own the קרקע. karka, עד שיחזיק
בזרעים, ad she'yachzik b'zra'im, until you do a חזקה chazaka because חזקה
chazaka doesn't work on מטלטלין. metaltelin It doesn't work on the seeds
indirectly. She didn't do the חזקה chazaka to the seeds, she did
it to the flowerpot. So the חזקה chazaka on the flowerpot was
nothing, didn't help for the seeds and it didn't help for the
flowerpot. Okay. Now we have another הלכה. halacha. נקבו בארץ ונופו בחוץ
לארץ. nikvah ba'aretz v'nofo b'chutz la'aretz. See there, Chava, you walk in
and then you get mentioned 10 times. Okay, we usually...
you should just know what we're saying about you when you're not
here.
I mean I'm happy it was this
case.
We weren't divorcing you perhaps. Okay.
זרעים zra'im
flowerpots are pretty, but
anyway
זרעים zra'im are considered קרקע, karka. that's what the assumption is?
Well, זרעים zra'im that are presumably in soil. If you actually have,
if you have a packet of seeds, right, then that's not קרקע.
karka Right, right, yeah. That's an interesting question. I wonder if you
had the seeds in the עציץ atzitz with the נקב nekev but
they weren't actually in dirt.
Not in the soil.
Yeah, that's what I... I don't know, if you had seeds lying
on ground would they... before they took before they took root. I
don't think so. I know. I think the זרעים, zra'im, I'm reading
the זרעים, zra'im, I'm reading it in the soil. I'm reading it
in the soil. Yeah. Okay.
Okay, now... okay. נקבו בארץ ונופו בחוץ
לארץ. nikvah ba'aretz v'nofo b'chutz la'aretz.
Now we get the גמרא Gemara has fun with this a number
of times. Here we have a case, we've got, you know the
old joke which is that if like a plane crashes and you
know, and and you know exactly on the borderline between, I don't
know, you know, between what would it be like, I don't know,
between... Maryland and Virginia, where are the survivors buried? The answer: survivors
aren't buried. Okay, so anyway, so you've got this flowerpot that's exactly
on the borderline
between, okay, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל. Bavel. Okay, it's exactly
whatever, חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, okay, and it is, okay, except the
flower, what does it say? It says ניקבו בארץ ונופו בחוץ לארץ.
nikvo be'aretz venofo bechutz la'aretz. Okay, so you've got it's on the
borderline there, here's your flowerpot, okay, it's got the hole, it's גיה,
geyah, okay, so it's connected to the dirt, but the flower, but
but the tree is sort of going over the line like this,
okay, and here are the fruit. All right, so is the fruit
חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות trumos uma'asros or not? Now, you're right
because the hole connects it to the ground in ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, but the actual foliage and the fruit is growing over the
line in חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Now you could have asked that
by a normal tree, which your גמרא Gemara does do in other
places, but here you could understand that there's more of a reason
to say that we treat it like חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. If
it's a real tree growing in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that's just
leaning over the border, right, you could say, okay, but it's growing
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the root and the trunk or whatever's
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it's an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael tree,
it's חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות, trumos uma'asros, and maybe the same
would be true in the reverse, true, right? But,
but in this case, in theory, the whole thing is movable. I
could just move the flowerpot and have it all in חוץ לארץ.
chutz la'aretz. So the degree to which it's considered, it's this weird
thing that's considered קרקע or מחובר לקרקע but it's movable. So maybe
it's movable למעשה lema'aseh and the fact that the actual fruit is
in the airspace of חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz and in theory the
whole thing could just be pushed over and be in חוץ לארץ,
chutz la'aretz, maybe that's enough to give it a חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz status. So that's the question. Okay, so let's take a look.
It has holes in the bottom. Yeah, that's what I was trying
to draw there. Okay, here's the hole.
Okay.
All right, so, all right, עציץ מקצתו בארץ ומקצתו, etzitz miktzato be'aretz
umiktzato,
I'm sorry, okay, okay, okay,
I know, we're up to גוזלים למידין gozalim lemidin later. Okay. ניקבו
בארץ ונופו בחוץ לארץ. nikvo be'aretz venofo bechutz la'aretz. אביי אמר בתר
ניקבו אזלינן, Abaye amar batar nikvo azlinan, you go by the hole
and it's an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael tree. רבא אמר בתר נופו
אזלינן, Rava amar batar nofo azlinan, you go by where it's growing
and it's a חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz tree. Now, by the way,
it's not necessarily clear that you would say the same in reverse,
like it could be that you require to be counted as ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you need both the נקב nekev and the נוף,
nof, right? You could imagine, right, it's not clear that you always
say that, you know, that it's just one of those things you'll
do the math. Anyway, but anyway, at least
in
this case, רבא Rava is saying that we treat it as a
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz tree. Okay. רבא אמר בתר נופו אזלינן, Rava
amar batar nofo azlinan, אביי אמר בתר ניקבו אזלינן, Abaye amar batar
nikvo azlinan, רבא אמר בתר נופו אזלינן. Rava amar batar nofo azlinan.
Now the גמרא Gemara explains. בדאשרוש, bed'ashrush, if it actually took root,
כולי עלמא לא פליגי, kulei alma lo pligi, that nobody disagrees. Then
it's basically a tree growing in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael which leaning
over to חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but it's an ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael tree, it took root, it really is in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. כי פליגי דלא אשרוש, ki pligi delo ashrush, course that it
didn't take root, that it's totally a movable tree. Okay. בדלא אשרוש.
bed'lo ashrush. And that's why רבא's Rava able to say that you
go by where the actual foliage is, because in theory you could
just move the flowerpot. So the גמרא Gemara says, ובדאשרוש לא פליגי,
uved'ashrush lo pligi, are you telling me when it actually took root
they don't debate? We could have that debate too even if it's
not movable.
והתנן, vehatnan, we taught in the משנה. שתי גנות, shti ginot, זו
על גב זו, zo al gav zo, וירק בינתים. veyerek beintayim. One
on top of the other
and there's a and there's a vegetable growing between them. So you
have these two gardens, here is ראובן's Reuven garden and here's שמעון's
Shimon garden, and you've got a plant that's growing like this out
of the dirt, right this is all dirt. Okay, so whose plant
is that? It's growing from ראובן's Reuven soil into שמעון's Shimon airspace.
All right, so,
how far off the ground is it?
It doesn't matter, you want but if you want to make me
happy it's עשרה טפחים, asara tfachim, but עשרה טפחים asara tfachim doesn't
matter in this case. It's all his airspace. Okay. רבי מאיר אמר
של עליון. Rabbi Meir omer shel elyon. It belongs to the guy
who owns the ground on top whose dirt it's growing from. רבי
יהודה אמר של תחתון, Rabbi Yehuda omer shel tachton, no, the guy
whose airspace it's in. So you see, that's the debate about do
we define something by the dirt it's growing from or the
airspace. So the גמרא Gemara says, התם כדיתני טעמא, hatam keditani ta'ama,
that's because of the reason we gave. אמר רבי מאיר מצי עליון
למישקל עפריה וליכא ירק, amar Rabbi Meir matzi elyon lemishkal afrei velika
yerek, that the guy could take his dirt and then there won't
be the vegetable, so that makes it belong to the guy at
top. אמר רבי יהודה לא מצי תחתון למלויי לגינתו עפר, amar Rabbi
Yehuda lo matzi tachton lemalo'ei leginato afar, but the guy on the
bottom can just fill up his airspace with dirt and וליכא ירק,
velika yerek, and that'll make it go away. So therefore, that's unrelated
to this. Now why is it unrelated to this? Why can't you
say, I don't know, in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz I could just
make a big mound of dirt and this won't have any space
to grow? So it seems that So it seems like what's really
makes it unrelated I mean is that that is a question about
ownership. And this is a right so ownership you could say if
I could control this thing I could sort of dig it up
right or take away the soil or fill it up and make
it you know and destroy it okay that's a question of who
possesses it who's more seen in possession of it and then we
can debate that in this case. This is not a question of
who possesses it it's not an ownership question right this is a
question about is it considered to be growing from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael to be חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות? Terumot u'Ma'asrot? Okay so
it's not the same question. So when it actually is rooted in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael everybody says it's growing from ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. Everybody could admit it's growing from ראובן's Reuven soil that doesn't
necessarily mean that ראובן Reuven possesses it. Okay so this is a
דיני ממונות dinei mamonot possession question but the גמרא Gemara is still
insisting that when it comes to the question about its status in
terms of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or חוץ לארץ Chutz L'Aretz it
could be that if it's actually taken root everybody agrees it goes
by where is the soil that it's growing from.
Okay it can be destroyed or not destroyed why isn't that a
question of whether it's מטלטלין metaltelin. or not?
No I don't know who said
you can I mean I
can cut down a tree it doesn't make מטלטלין.
In two ways you have to draw that line.
No no it's not. So אמר ליה אביי ודילמא בהא לא פליגי
Amar leh Abaye v'dilma b'ha lo pligi are you still
going to say that they don't debate when it's taken root? So
fine that's not relevant. That's a question of דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot.
Okay? But I still want to argue even when it comes to
the issue about ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael status it makes a difference
if it's taken root. I mean they would debate even in a
case where it took root. והתניא Veha tanya we learned a ברייתא
Beraita אילן מקצתו בארץ ומקצתו בחוצה לארץ ilan m'ktzato b'aretz u'm'ktzato b'chutz
la'aretz exactly this! A tree that's growing partly in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael partly in חוץ לארץ. Chutz L'Aretz. טבל וחולין מעורבין זה בזה
דברי רבי Tebel v'chullin m'uravin zeh b'zeh divrei Rabbi Rabbi says it's
טבל tebel and חולין chullin mixed up with one another every fruit
is half and half. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר הגדל בחיוב חייב
הגדל בפטור פטור. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer hagadel b'chiyuv chayav hagadel
b'pattur pattur. What grows in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is חייב chayav
and what grows in חוץ לארץ Chutz L'Aretz is פטור. pattur. Now
what would be a case that you could identify the side that
grows in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael as opposed to side that grows
in חוץ לארץ? Chutz L'Aretz? What does it mean it's half growing?
So you could imagine two scenarios of half growing right you could
imagine a scenario of half growing like this right that the tree
is sort of like growing like that. But then how could you
identify which half is growing in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael which half
is growing in חוץ לארץ? Chutz L'Aretz? Presumably if you're identifying which
half is where it means that the actual wherever it's the actual
foliage right sort of covers both. I'm trying to sort of whatever.
And then so if the actual foliage covers both you know you
got the fruit in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and the fruit in
חוץ לארץ Chutz L'Aretz and you can identify which is which. So
you're dividing the fruit based on where the fruit is growing the
air space where the foliage is. The foliage in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the foliage in חוץ לארץ Chutz
L'Aretz is חוץ לארץ. Chutz L'Aretz. So you see here's a case
where we sort of ignore where it's taking root nobody is discussing
where it's rooted and we're just saying is the fruit on this
side of the line or the fruit on that side of the
line? So that sounds like a case of a tree that even
wherever it's taking root its status is defined by where the foliage
is. Is that clear? Yes? Because if the foliage right the very
fact that we can imagine splitting where did the fruit grow on
which side of the line we're talking about where the fruit is
growing which side of the tree it's coming off of. So presumably
we're looking at the foliage as defining is it in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and חוץ לארץ Chutz L'Aretz and we're not where the
actual trunk of the tree is.
Okay but this might be a special case where it's divided by
the roots. You're saying we're not...
Well
so the question is... So well the גמרא Gemara assumes that maybe
it's irrelevant where the roots are. We're going to say that... But
the גמרא Gemara assumes that if we're focusing on where the fruit
is growing the only thing that matters is where the fruit is
and not where the roots are. That's what the גמרא Gemara assumes.
That's what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. Okay. But for now the
גמרא Gemara is assuming that...
Just like in the previous case we are...
Right. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that in this case not because
this case only focuses on where the fruit is growing. Let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו mai lav is it
not that the ability to discuss which side the fruit is growing
is a case of מקצת נופה בארץ ומקצת נופה בחוצה לארץ m'ktzat
nofah b'aretz u'm'ktzat nofah b'chutz la'aretz that half of the foliage is
on one side half on the other and it's irrelevant where the
trunk of the tree is? So you see that even in a
case where it's taken root we could focus totally on the foliage
and that proves that you can go by that. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא no מקצת שרשין בארץ ומקצת שרשין בחוצה לארץ m'ktzat
shorashin b'aretz u'm'ktzat shorashin b'chutz la'aretz
who said... Who said that it's only the question about the foliage?
Maybe we're talking about the actual trunk is also on the borderline
the roots? But the גמרא Gemara has got a problem. If the
trunk and the roots are on the borderline how can you say
the part that grows... If you're focusing not on... It's not just
a physical question. If you would say it's defined as where the
tree is you could say this part of the tree is on
this side and this part is on this side. But if you
say the tree's identity is defined from the ground that it's growing
in right and it's growing here from both ground from both places
how can you say
the part that grows in
חיוב? chiyuv? and not on the fruit, right? That's the idea that
you go if you focus on the ground and not the fruit,
right, then everything should be a mix because all of the whole
tree is being nurtured from both ground. If you focus on just
where the fruit is, you could say the simple way of understanding
this debate, I don't know simple, but a reasonable way of understanding
this debate is one approach says the tree's identity is where it's
getting its nutrients from. Since it's getting its nutrients from both, it's
in both land, it actually is a mix of טבל *tevel* and
and and חולין *chullin* because it's being fed by both lands. And
the other says I don't care where it's getting its nutrients from,
I care where the fruit is growing. Half the fruit is growing
here and half the fruit is growing there. Okay. So a good
way of explaining that debate is whether you go by where it's
where it's where it's, you know, where it's growing from or where
the fruits are coming or the airspace of the fruit. But if
we are saying that the position even about even about the fruit
is if focuses defines the tree based on the where it's planted,
so who cares that it just because it's planted here doesn't mean
that these half of the fruits grow from this nutrient and these
half from that's not the way it works. Okay. So basically what
it's saying is yes, physically we're talking that it's planted in the
middle and the the fruits are divided. But a position that says
you split the fruit, how could that position define something based on
where it's planted? If you define it based on where it's planted,
it doesn't work that the nutrients just go that way, right? They
all see the whole tree. So it should be then a mix.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is that'll help
clarify it. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא מקצתו בציציתו בחוצה ומקצתו
בציציתו בפנים *Lo miktzaso b'tzitzito bachutza umiktzaso b'tzitzito bifnim*. ומאי טעמא דרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל *Umai ta'ama d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*? So how could
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* if you are defined,
if you're claiming that when it's really taken root in the ground,
everybody defines it by where it's planted, so how could רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* say you split the tree half
and half? So the גמרא *Gemara* says because we're talking about a
special case. דמפסיק צונמא *Dmafsik tsunma*, that there's a rock that divides
it. Okay. So basically what we're talking about is is that it's
a special case where there actually is a protruding rock here that
actually comes up the tree along the like like this and actually,
you know, these roots and it goes down into the ground and
it runs along the line of the runs along the line of
the borderline here, okay. So actually, this rock prevent makes it that
all of these roots are on one side and all of these
roots are come down on the other side of the border. Okay.
So that act there actually is a way in which the roots
don't, you know, criss-cross underground, even underground the roots are separate, the
roots on this side of the of the border are only, you
know, only go down on this side and the roots on this
side only go down on that side. Okay. So underground they don't
criss-cross because there's a rock that goes deep into the ground that
keeps them separate. Very nice says the גמרא *Gemara*, but how about
once they get into the tree? Okay. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says so מאי טעמא דרבי *mai ta'ama d'Rabbi*? So
why does רבי *Rabbi* say that the whole tree is a mix?
דהדרי ערבי *Dhadri arvai*, so that they the nutrients get mixed up
once it gets into the tree. במאי קמיפלגי *Bmai kamifligi*, what do
they debate? מר סבר אוירא מבלבל *Mar savar avira mivallbel*, that once
it gets into out of the ground and gets into the trunk
of the tree, it all gets mixed together in the air, not
in the air, but whatever, above ground. ומר סבר האי לחודיה קאי
והאי לחודיה קאי *Umar savar hai l'chudai kai v'hai l'chudai kai*. As
long as underground the roots remain separate on their side of the
line, even when the nutrients get into the tree, they just continue
to feed their side of the tree. Okay. I have I doubt
that's true but I really have no idea. Anyway, so the point
that the גמרא *Gemara* is saying is if you're going to say
you split the fruit, it sounds like you're ignoring the the question
of where it's planted. Because if you pay attention to where it's
planted and where it's getting its nutrients, it should all be a
mix. The ability to only focus on the fruit seems to say
it doesn't matter what's going on down here, it only matters what's
going on up there. And the גמרא *Gemara* says no, we could
say that it does matter what's going on down here and construct
a case where it remains separate even below, which allows me to
say you split the fruit on top as well. Yes.
When when I encountered the words ומבלבל *u'mivallbel*, that they would mix
in טבל וחולין *tevel v'chullin*,
particularly
since they have to come up with this very specialized case of
the rock, I understood the פשט *pshat* was that each individual piece
of fruit would be a mixture.
It is, correct. That's
רבי *Rabbi*'s position. Right. Each individual piece of fruit.
And you don't know it's not like
half is טבל *tevel*
and half in this area.
Exactly. No, that's רבי *Rabbi* as opposed to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
*Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*, who splits it, this half and this half.
That's exactly the debate.
Well, this half and this half
is...
No, but meaning the half, the fruit that grows on this side
of the line and the fruit that grows, that's רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל.
Right, but the mixture one is all the fruit on the tree.
Exactly.
Exactly. Exactly. That's both ends. So anyway, this is a case that
the גמרא has a lot of fun with in general, which is
a tree grown in one place and the foliage and the fruit
in another. Here it seems that here the גמרא is inclined to
say that if you follow the foliage you could follow the foliage
here even if normally you would go by where it's planted, but
here it's fundamentally movable. So here since it's fundamentally movable, you could
go by the foliage and say in theory it could all be
on the same side of the line as where the foliage is,
okay, but it could be that when it's really taken root, it
could be in that case everybody would agree it goes by the
soil from which it's growing, although this case makes it sound like
that might be debatable, the גמרא had a way of dealing with
that. Yes.
What's the theoretical that I can also do with this, what if
you have a shrub? Like a shrub is like a lot of
little plants. Yeah. Okay, so there's one on this side, one on
that side, one on this side, one on that side, and then
all the foliage is like mixed together.
Is that is
there...
That would be a more of a classic case of the growing
in one side and the foliage on another.
No, but you can't tell where the foliage was coming from in
a shrub. You can't. You can't tell. It's like...
Right. Right.
So... Yeah, but I mean to the degree that it would be
coinciding... anyway, but it would we'd have to deal with the ספק
safek element, but fundamentally it's a case where it's planted in one
and the foliage grows into another space. Okay. So anyway, that's the
fun case the גמרא has elsewhere. Clearly if it's actually that it's
a case with an עציץ נקוב, it allows you more to discount
the ground and to follow the foliage. If it's actually taken root,
it's much more likely that you would just go by where it
is growing from. Okay. Back to the more גיטין Gittin cases. רבי
יהודה בן בתירא אומר. Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer. Now we're back
to רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira saying that you
don't write it on a piece of paper that is already erased
or that can be... what do you call it? Or that's דפתרא
diftera which can be erased. Now by the way, the point is
is that the question is is that the witness's signature appears on,
here's the key. Because if you know, the witness's signature appears on
over an erasure or on this דפתרא diftera and because the witness's
signature appears there, anything you make above won't look suspicious because it'll
be consistent right with the like if you erase the stuff on
top and rewrite something and you go ah well we can't accept
that it's written on an erasure but look the witness's signature is
also on an erasure. So right so that will make it all
look consistent, but if the witness's signature is written on imagine I
come to a document it's the witness's signature is clean on a
clean background and the top is all erased obviously you'd throw it
out it's clear what I did right? I took a nice document
and I erased the top but if the witness's signature is on
the erasure and then I'm writing the top on the erasure I'll
just re-erase the stuff on the top and replace it and it'll
all look very consistent. So that's why that it's not acceptable, but
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda but the חכמים Chachamim say it's okay. So
let's take a look at this. רבי יהודה בן בתירא אומר. Rabbi
Yehuda ben Beteira omer. אמר רבי חייא בר אסי משמיה דעולא. Amar
Rabbi Chiyya bar Ashi mishmeih de-Ulla. ג' עורות הן: Gimmel orot hen:
there are three types of parchment or whatever leathers. מצה חיפה ודפתרא.
Matza, chippa, ve-diftera. So מצה Matza is כמשמעו. ke-mashmao. מצה Matza is
like it sounds like like מצה, Matza, you know, not fancy, thin,
whatever although their מצה Matza was not our cracker מצה Matza but
anyway. דלא מליח ודלא קמיח ודלא אפיץ. D-lo maliach ve-d-lo kammiach ve-d-lo
afitz. It's leather that has not been salted or treated with flour
and it is not or the gallnuts, untreated leather.
ולמאי הלכתא U-le-mai hilchata so why is it important to know to
know the identity you know what is that category? להוצאת שבת. Le-hotza'at
Shabbat. וכמה שיעורו? Ve-kamma shiuro? Because to tell me the minimum amount
of carrying for that on שבת. Shabbat. כדתני רבי שמואל בר יהודה...
Ki-de-tani Rabbi Shmuel bar Yehuda... כדתני רבי שמואל בר יהודה כדי לצור
משקולת קטנה Ki-de-tani Rabbi Shmuel bar Yehuda kedi latzur mishkolet ketanna
because you would use it not to write on but you'd use
it to wrap little weights. And therefore even the amount that you
would use to wrap a small weight that would be an amount
of significance and you'd be חייב chayav for carrying on שבת. Shabbat.
וכמה? Ve-kamma? How much of that would you use to wrap a
small weight or how much of a weight would you wrap with
that? ואמר אביי: Ve-amar Abaye: כריבעא דריבעא דפומבדיתא Ke-riva de-riva de-Pumbedita which
is the smallest like I don't know a half a gram or
whatever the smallest weight that they would use to wrap so the
weights don't get worn away in that they're you know and they
don't weigh what they're supposed to weigh. חיפה Chippa now what's חיפה?
Chippa? דמליח ולא קמיח. De-maliach ve-lo kammiach. It's leather that's been salted
but has not been treated with the flour. ולא אפיץ Ve-lo afitz
or the gallnut. ולמאי הלכתא? U-le-mai hilchata? What's relevant to know that
category? להוצאת שבת Le-hotza'at Shabbat same point because it has a different
use and therefore a different שיעור. shiur. וכמה שיעורו? Ve-kamma shiuro? What
is the amount?
כדתנן Ki-detnan or כדי לעשות קמיע. kedi la'asot kamia. Because you would
use it you'd use it for a קמיע kamia for an amulet.
Now you could think it means to write an amulet although רש"י
Rashi says it means you would use it to wrap an amulet.
Maybe it's not able to be written on. Anyway that's what you
would use those things for and maybe they'd be you know and
that that would be the size for carrying on שבת.
Shabbat. Also they
sew the amulet.
Right.
Right. דפתרא דמליח וקמיח ולא אפיץ. Diftera de-maliach ve-kammiach ve-lo afitz. דפתרא
Diftera is salted and treated with this flour but it's not with
this gallnut. Once it's with
the
gallnut... Whereas when you have actual קלף, Klaf, you would use קלף
Klaf which is more expensive, the שיעור shiur is to write the
פרשה קטנה שבתפילין. parsha katana she-be-Tefillin. Okay, cause that's what you would
use with קלף Klaf is you'd use it for כתבי קודש. kisvei
kodesh. Okay, וחכמים מכשירין. ve-Chachamim makhshirin. Now we're going to get to
this debate, why should such a thing be kosher if it's forgeable?
So וחכמים, ve-Chachamim, who are the חכמים? Chachamim? אמר אלעזר, Amar Elazar,
oh look at this, we're going to finish the דף. daf. אמר
רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, although whatever. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar היא,
it's רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי, that says you
go by the witnesses that see it being handed over, and therefore
even though it's forgeable, okay, what you could always do is you
could always say well now we're just going to, we wouldn't rely
on it anyway because according to רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar we always
want to get the witnesses to tell us what they saw and
that's why it's not a problem that it's written on something that
could be forged because we would always anyway have to hear from
the witnesses who were present. ואמר רבי אלעזר Ve-amar Rabbi Elazar לא
הכשיר רבי אלעזר אלא לאלתר. lo hikhshir Rabbi Elazar ela le-altar. Even
if רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar allowed us to use such a document,
it was only together with the testimony of the witnesses, it was
only if the witnesses came to בית דין Beis Din and testified
right away that it were up to the divorce. אבל מכאן ועד
עשרה ימים לא. Aval mikan ve-ad asara yamim lo.
But if it would be like ten days later, you know,
he would not allow. Why not? We're still going by what the
witnesses saw. Because חיישינן דילמא הוי בה תנאי וזייפתה. chashinan dilma havei
bei tenai ve-zayafteh. We're afraid that there was a condition and it
was forged. Meaning, well what we're afraid about what we're afraid of,
but what about the fact that we go by witnesses that were
actually present? We're not afraid about forgery because we're not just relying
on the signatures. So the point is people's memory is not perfect,
right? So therefore it's one, so what way, one way to understand
I mean there's a huge תוספות Tosafos to sort of navigate, you
know, how this plays out according to the two positions. But here's
one way the תוספות Tosafos says. If you're saying רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir עדי חתימה כרתי, edei chasima karsi, what makes it into a
document is that it testi-, it sort of, it test-, you know,
it provides its own testimony. Any document that is forgeable that you
can't rely on for the testimony that's in it, according to רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir. is not a document because רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
says what defines it as a document is the signatures that it's
מוכח מתוכו, mukhach mitocho, that it testifies for itself and anything that's
מזוייף מתוכו, mezuyyaf mitocho, even if in theory for רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir, you could call the witnesses over and have them tell you
what happened, it wouldn't matter. It wouldn't be a גט get. if
it's not testifying effectively on its own about what happened. Okay, that's
רבי מאיר. But רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says I don't need it
to testify on its own what happened to be a גט. get
Good, it's a גט, get it's a good instrument for divorce. The
only problem is is that even if it's a good instrument for
divorce, how do we trust what happened? That's a separate question, right?
One question is does it function to free this woman? There's another
question which is how do we rely on it? So רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar oh you want to rely on it, go call the
witnesses. Okay, but you know what? Witnesses sometimes their memory isn't perfect.
So after a certain period of time you won't be able to
actually fully trust the witnesses and that's why he says that he
only trusted him לאלתר le-altar and not מכאן ועד עשרה ימים. mikan
ve-ad asara yamim. It's true the document is and can't be relied
on. It can still function as a גט, get, okay, but if
you want to know how do we know what happened, you'd better
get the witnesses to testify right away because after a while if
the document was not forgeable then we could combine their memory with
the document, yes I recognize that document, that was the document we
used, and therefore we fill in the blanks based on their testimony
and the document. But with a forgeable document we're only relying on
their memory and therefore we'd better get them to testify right away.
Okay.
רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים, Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu
mikan ve-ad asara yamim, even from now for ten days, דאי איתא
דהוה בה תנאי מדכר דכירי, de-ee is-sa de-havei bei tenai midkar dakhiri,
they would remember and it's not a problem. Okay, and אמר so
that's a, so that again it's a question of figuring out exactly
how the different positions play it. But the easy way to understand
is for רבי מאיר that עדי חתימה כרתי, eidei chasima kartei, something
that is forgeable is forget that it can't prove that she's divorced,
cannot function as a גט. get A גט get. has to be
a document whose testimony is clear from within it, and for him
it's nothing. For רבי אלעזר it functions as a גט get. and
we can debate whether we can trust the witnesses to remember the
specifics afterwards. Okay. Now the גמרא says like this.
אמר רבי אלעזר לא הכשיר רבי אלעזר אלא בגיטין. Amar Rabbi Elazar
lo hikhshir Rabbi Elazar ela be-gittin. When רבי אלעזר allowed such a
forgeable document it was only for a גט, אבל בשאר שטרות לא,
aval bi-shear shetaros lo, not other documents, דכתיב ונתתם בכלי חרס למען
יעמדו ימים רבים, de-khsiv u-nesasam bi-khli cheres le-maan yaamdu yamim rabbim, other
documents have to be able to be and that was about writing
a bill of sale to actually be usable for a long period
of time. Now תוספות Tosafos says what's in the other documents category?
תוספות Tosafos is inclined to say what that means and here's a
very important conceptual distinction which we've even been spinning along but I'm
just going to give you the key words. Is it a שטר
קנין shtar kinyan or is it a שטר ראיה? shtar raya? A
שטר קנין shtar kinyan is a document that functions as an instrument,
so that is to free, to divorce a wife, to free a
slave, or to transfer ownership of a field, of a piece of
property. But that's not necessarily to prove who owns the property. I
could write on this piece of paper שדה מכורה לך sade makhura
lakha and give it to you and that might be sufficient to
transfer ownership even though it's not sufficient to prove exactly what happened.
So תוספות Tosafot says that when you're dealing with a שטר קנין,
shtar kinyan, that's when רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it doesn't have
to testify to anything and it could be forgeable. But if you're
dealing with שאר שטרות, shear shtarot, doesn't mean all other שטרות, shtarot,
it means שטרות shtarot that are שטר ראיה. shtar raya. The whole
purpose of the שטר shtar is to prove what happened, that you
borrowed a thousand dollars from me, to prove which piece of property
I own. Everybody would agree that a שטר shtar like that only
functions if it is, you know, not forgeable and if it can
testify to itself and if you can look at it many days
later and it can have the same, and the testimony is reliable.
Okay, והכתיב ונתתם בכלי חרס למען יעמדו ימים רבים. v'hakhtiv u'netatim bikhli
cheres lema'an ya'amdu yamim rabim. רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar אפילו
בשטרות, afilu beshtarot, even other שטרות. shtarot.
Now what good is something that's forgeable? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
presumably is saying you combine the memory of the witnesses with the
שטר. shtar. Then who needs a שטר shtar if witnesses are testifying?
Well, maybe you need a שטר shtar because if I borrow money
from you with a שטר, shtar, you have lien, and if I
borrow without a שטר, shtar, you don't have lien, right? So maybe
that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying. Okay, but רבי יוחנן
is saying even other שטרות shtarot you can use it with somehow
a forgeable document together with the actual witnesses. והכתיב למען יעמדו ימים
רבים, v'hakhtiv lema'an ya'amdu yamim rabim, but doesn't it say they have
to last a long time? So that's עצה טובה קמשמע לן. eitzah
tovah ka mashma lan. That was just giving you good advice. If
you want to use your document, you'll do it in a way
that you can use it after a long time, but it's not
a requirement of the document. So we have here a very critical
issue in הלכות גט, Hilchos Get, maybe I'll repeat it again tomorrow
because we were a little rushed, but just to say what in
one sentence: for רבי מאיר, a גט that is עדי חתימה כרתי,
that does not testify for itself what happened, cannot serve as an
instrument of divorce. It's not just not a ראיה, raya, if it's
not a ראיה raya it's not a גט. For רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, even though it's no longer a ראיה, raya, it can still
serve as a שטר קנין shtar kinyan as an instrument for divorce.
Okay, and then there's a question: can we trust the witnesses to
remember what happened? But that's a separate question, proving it. Okay, but
it can still function as a שטר קנין. shtar kinyan. And then
the גמרא wants to know what would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say
by שאר שטרות? shear shtarot? Does שאר שטרות shear shtarot mean other
שטר קנין, shtar kinyan, maybe like a שחרור של עבד shichrur shel
eved or transferring a field? Maybe there he would agree it have
to be, it have to be also a שטר ראיה. shtar raya.
That's one way of saying it. Or is he saying no no,
every other שטר קנין shtar kinyan is like a גט. It doesn't
have to be a שטר ראיה. shtar raya. But something that's a
שטר ראיה, shtar raya, that better be something that is able to
testify for itself, that you can't rely on testimony external to the
document for the document to be a שטר ראיה. shtar raya. It
obviously have to, there he would obviously agree that it has to
function and it has to be able to be written on something
that is not forgeable and can actually serve as testimony as a
form of written testimony. And the נפקא מינה nafka mina would
be...